Nicole: All organisations and
companies will have an IT policy
in place, and some may even have
a specific cyber security policy.
All policies should be adhered to
consistently from the top down.
They should be clear and current
being reviewed and updated by the
senior management team at least
annually, and in touch with ever
changing laws and regulations.
There should be no barriers to
complying with policy guidelines
and procedures and where necessary
training should be provided.
There should also be regular audits
to check that policy is being followed
and all employees are on track.
Most new employees must sign up to
a policy agreement as part of their
induction to say that they will follow
the guidelines before they are given
their emails and log in details.
Policy guidelines may be different
depending on the business or organisation
and the data that employees are working
with but overall, the guidelines
will be the same for everyone.
Where any specific sensitive
data is concerned there may be
extra level of security involved
and different rules may apply.
Where data is concerned guidelines
should be always followed
strictly adhering to GDPR rules.
There are a range of ethical rules that
link to legislation when it comes to
using computer systems that apply such as:
Not using computer
equipment to harm others.
Not interfering with
other’s computers and work
Not looking through other’s
files without their permission.
Not using a computer to
steal or cause mischief.
Not copying software.
Not using other people’s
resources without permission.
Acting without regard for consequences.
And having respect for data security.
With remote working, many more
employees are working from home
and these rules should still apply.
Many employees now sync their work
emails to their smartphones, which may
involve employers expecting workers
to check emails outside office hours.
Cyber security is even more important
especially when personal emails are
accessed alongside business emails.
Many businesses will set up their
employees for remote working but in
some cases, it may involve an employee
taking their laptop home and relying
on their own internet security set up.
All IT policy guidelines regarding
data security and misuse of computers
should be still adhered to even more so.
Unethical conduct can be something as
simple as leaving a 'post it' around
with log details for anyone to access
a computer system as this can open a
system up to unethical security issues.
This may just be thoughtless
behaviour or a lack of judgement,
but it can lead to so much more.
It may involve deliberately copying
information and data to use or supply
to others for unethical activities.
Unethical behaviour can involve
sabotage, disclosing or misusing
confidential information or maliciously
injuring the reputation or prospects
of an individual or business.
It’s also important to remember
that as cyber security professionals
we have a great deal of access to
sensitive data and it’s important
that we do not use this high level
of access for the wrong purposes.